Software Engineering Radio episode 26
interview with Jutta Eckstein.
Hi everybody. Today we are sitting in
Wiesbaden together with Jutta Eckstein.
And she is an expert on Agile software
development and several other process
things. And it's great that you took the
time to talk with us for Software
Engineering Radio.
Jutta, maybe you'd like to introduce
yourself.
Yeah, you you mentioned it already. So
I'm
mainly
working in Agile software development
for the past few years. And my focus is
on large projects.
So that's also where where I came from
because most of the people they
described Agile development in smaller
teams or for smaller teams. So saying
for 10 12 people. And my focus is in in
larger settings, large organizations. So
up to let's say 250 300 people in a
working on a project. And
well, also meanwhile, that's also true
for Agile development that those teams
are distributed over the globe. So it's
also distributed development in in a
Agile setting.
That sounds really cool. But before we
go into the large-scale distributed
Agile things,
could you explain what Agile development
is and what's special about Agile
projects, about Agile project management
as opposed to more classical approaches,
maybe?
To me the the major difference is maybe
that different to other proponents of
Agile development is that Agile
development is
for first and
most important a value system.
So, it's defined as a value system and
it's defined
in terms of principles.
Whereas a lot of people always assume
Agile development is a specific process
or consists of specific practices.
But yeah, staying for for the practices
for example,
pair programming is one of the practices
a lot of people know about and and they
mention it, but you can use pair
programming in every kind of process.
So, you can follow a waterfall approach
and still use pair programming. So, this
doesn't mean anything about agility.
That's what what I mean by
Agile development is a value system and
then using that value system as a
guidance for coming up for with
practices
that help you and your team to stay
Agile.
And well, the value system itself is
described in a manifesto. You want me to
repeat the manifesto? No. Yes?
Yeah, that would really be great.
So, the the core of the Agile manifesto
says that
individuals and interactions are more
important than processes and tools. So,
this is the first
pair of values which is compared and it
it means that both things have value.
So, individuals and interactions are
valuable as well as processes and tools.
But if it comes down to it, then
um
individuals and interactions have a
higher value than processes and tools.
So, this is this is true for all value
pair comparisons.
And um for emphasizing that both sides
have a value.
Um you can also see that Agile processes
are questioning themselves because they
say individuals and interactions are
more important than processes. And also
that you can see that a lot of tools
have been developed in the Agile
community like all the unit testing
frameworks, the refactoring tools, the
I don't know, a lot of stuff has been
coming out of the Agile development. So
tools are important, but if it comes
down to it, individuals and interactions
are more important than processes and
tools. The The next value pair um
is
I don't know if that's the right order.
It doesn't really matter. It's working
software
over comprehensive documentation. And
again, it this is probably the
thing that is the most misunderstood in
Agile development. That people think if
you follow an Agile approach, you don't
document. But this is not true. So we
have a lot of documentation. Sometimes
maybe not as traditional and classic as
it's used somewhere else. For example,
we have a lot of things like photo
protocols or or we have wikis where we
document a lot. So we use maybe other
tools for documentation, but we also
have classic documentation if it's
required. However, it's more important
to have working software. So it's not a
documentation driven process, but it's a
a process which has in focus to have
working software at the end of the day.
Um okay, then we have the next value
pair, customer collaboration over
contract negotiation.
Again, I at least I have never been on
Agile process without any contract.
You know, so contracts are something
which is is a thing that is settled and
it's used and it's important, but it's
more important to collaborate with the
customer because at the end of the day
the customer decides if your project is
successful or not. And it doesn't matter
if at the end you figure out that in the
contract any
thing different has been specified, if
the customer now has changed his mind
and and says, "Well, this is what I need
now, although I stated something else at
the beginning." Then this is what he
needs now. This makes the success of the
project if you are able to figure out
that.
Um, which leads me to the last value
pair, which is welcoming change over
following a plan. So, this is kind of
similar to what I've talked about right
now. This is not focused on the
contract, but on your plan you often
make in the project at the beginning.
And one thing would be sticking to that
plan and try to control against that
plan, and the other thing is to welcome
changes and adjust your plan according
to those changes. So, the value system
says it's more important to welcome
those changes and then make those
adjustments and not following your plan.
So, if you define Agile processes as a
value system, then that means that you
probably have to customize the
development process for each and every
project depending on the size, on the
context, on the maybe on on potentially
safety or other formal requirements. So,
is it fair to say that one of your
primary tasks as a coach in this context
is to customize and improve the process?
That's very true. So, this is the the
main job of a process coach, to figure
out what's needed for the specific team,
for a specific project, and find the
process that supports the exactly that
team, that project. However, there are
some some guidance and the guidance
mainly is the value system
along with the principles that undermine
the value system. And of course, you can
use the practices defined in the
different Agile processes and maybe they
help you in your specific context, but
maybe they don't. As I said, one example
was the was the pair programming, but
you could use whatever practice you know
from extreme programming. So, it could
tell, but it must not be the the best
practices in your circumstance.
Could you give us examples of practices
that you've used in small projects like
five or six or seven people and
practices that you use in larger
projects like 200 people and maybe other
practices that can be used in all kinds
of settings. I would guess that for
example, testing is something that you
would test driven development is
something you could use in all these
settings. So, what are the different
typically different best practices that
you use in those different scales of
Agile development?
For example, in a small project, I I
didn't believe it at the beginning,
honestly, but I figured out that in a
small project that you mentioned, six or
seven people, I would say I think we had
like 12 developers and in total with the
other people around, it was like 20.
We were able to get it get along very
very well without chief architect.
Meaning that if a team is really small,
this is really a
joint responsibility of everyone to
focusing on the architecture. And if
there specific decisions made, then they
just wrote a flip chart and this was
like the guidance for the next few weeks
and everyone knows and till the next
major decision came up. And that's
worked perfectly. And I think I was the
one doubting it the most at the
beginning that this could ever work. But
this is one of the
um practices suggested by extreme
programming. Everyone is a generalist.
Everyone has the same kind of
responsibility and things like that. And
this
does completely not work in a large
setting. So, if you have a large
project, you need a single one person
who makes the decisions regarding
architecture, for example. Of course,
there are other people suggesting such
um decisions and and so on and helping
to come up with something. But, there
must be one chief architect you you know
you can go to and ask for a specific
decision or who will bring together the
key ideas and will make sure that the
vision is taking over for the whole
project and so on. And this is not
required for small team because the team
really itself can carry that vision
forward. And this is I would say a major
difference.
Coming back, the last thing you were
asking were asking about was um what's
the the same thing all over the place.
Um
sometimes I say, "Well, I have I have
kind of my principles and it's really
hard to convince me otherwise." Although
I say you have to adjust the process
according what's needed and so on. And
um a major principle is the having short
iterations. And the iterations, if they
are short, it's easier to plan them
because they you don't have to look so
much ahead of time and you are also then
able to measure what you have planned
against. And well, I have seen projects
without short iterations and they never
figured out, for example, how much they
can achieve. And so, it's hard to know
if they can make the deadline or not.
And and so, the the shortness of
iterations, they this is something you
will need always, I would say.
Um these values and these value pairs
with one of them more
valuable than the other, valued over the
other,
um appear to be about trust at the core.
I mean, contracts are sort of a
safeguard against
when trust goes overboard or
documentation is sort of a or is often
used as a safeguard against things going
wrong. So, it appears to me that as long
as
both parties trust each other, things go
fine.
But, how do you gain the trust, build
the trust before a project is started?
How do you keep trust alive in crisis
when probably management has the reflex
to fall back into cover your ass mode,
something like that?
You're very right with that. That's very
true that it's Trust is really something
very important, but I think it's
also it's important in all kinds of
projects. So, it's kind of independent
of the process. And if you are in a
state where you
have to come back to to your contract
saying, "But this is what we have
written there." then you're already in a
state where
where it's all downhill. You have lost
already. If you argue on that state, the
project will never be a success.
And um it's on on a different level, but
it's also true with documentation. If
you use documentation
because of mistrust saying like, "But
there you said this and that and look at
that protocol."
If you have to argue that way, then a
lot is lost already and you have
problems that you have to figure out at
first and have to solve them.
Okay, that's that's kind of supporting
your your statement. Um
What do you do for building trust? I I
think the the most important thing is to
communicate face-to-face and this is
true for all settings. Again, if it's
small or large or whatever for building
up trust, you need direct communication
and I can give you an example
away from processes and all that stuff
just a a kind of a non thing I guess
everyone has experienced in his life.
When I I used to work for Park Place,
that's way back and when I started
working there
and we we were here in the office in
Germany and when we had difficult
questions to the engineers in um
California
I had really
very very much difficulties to get in to
get an answer to my difficult questions,
but then there was a time when I the
first time get over and talk to those
people. So, I met them in person and saw
them and had the face-to-face
communication starting from there.
I always get got very
uh quick feedback on my questions
because they knew me and they knew what
kind of person I am and so they were
more willing to reply because beforehand
it was just oh just another one asking
whatever kind of questions I'm busy
already, but if there is a a person you
know behind that email, phone and so on,
then you are you have a
a different relationship to that person
and that is true for all the processes.
So, having face-to-face meetings is
definitely useful for building trust at
at the same level between colleagues,
between co-workers, but how do you gain
the trust of management
to have the courage
to depart from their
from the old processes they are used to?
I mean, this is a huge step for
management to trust someone to work in
an agile way with them
and work without all these documents
that are sort sort of serve as a
safeguard in in classical software
development. We're interested to hear
some some practices, some approaches
that or some stories maybe that worked.
Okay, there are several things to say.
First of all,
why do you think that face-to-face
communication will not work across
hierarchy levels? So,
again, also there it's very important
that people know each other, that they
have
at least met once in a while and and so
they know there are persons behind. So,
this is true also across hierarchies.
Um
the other thing is which convinces
management the most is working software.
Because if if you can show after an
iteration what you have achieved and you
do this iteration for iterations, then
also if it goes down,
then people remember that they were able
to produce some software and there must
be a reason why it doesn't work at the
moment like that and maybe we have to
help them and change something. So, it's
it's more like
yeah, people yeah, they they build trust
by seeing people are doing something and
it's not like like this blind trust you
often have to have in other projects
where you just see that there is I don't
know another pound of documents
developed, but you don't know if this
means anything or maybe you think they
look pretty and so that's why they must
be good or so, but you cannot really
judge. But if you see a running system,
it's different. And it it's also true,
for example, not only across
hierarchies, also across companies.
So, what we also often do is we invite
the customers
well well, often do the sounds a bit
strange, but I'm also often in companies
where we develop for the for the own
company, so it's it's inside the company
still. But even if the customer is
outside the company, then we also invite
the customer at least at the end of the
iteration to come there and to look at
the software and provide the feedback
and this builds trust.
But of course, it still can go down and
this is actually one of the risks I
always see in in HR projects. If you
start in an HR manner, then
well,
people are very excited and they focus
on working software and they will
produce for the first three iterations
a lot of stuff and
management and the customer gets very
very excited and I always warn them that
it will not stay that way, that there
will be times where we will not be able
to produce that much. So it's it's kind
of a pre-warning
and
yeah, interesting.
You mentioned the term iteration
sometimes. Can you explain to us what an
iteration is and what is going on in
such an iteration?
This is a good question.
One thing is you have to figure out
what's the
perfect length for your iteration and
there are two main guidances for the
iteration length. One is how often does
somebody want to change the priorities
or come up with new requirements or
change requirements.
So you have to
be able to act on those changes and if
you act on those changes during the
iteration, then there's no need to plan
and measure that iteration because
everything you planned and and will
measure has changed in the meantime. So
you you have to keep the the thing
you're working at working on during an
iteration fixed and if there are a lot
of changes required, this means your
iteration is too long.
So, that's one guidance of the iteration
length. The other one is how much
overhead do you have like
reviewing the iteration, planning the
next one. If this is this has to be in a
balance. If you takes half the time of
your iteration to plan and review it,
then probably also something is wrong
with the iteration length.
So,
most of the projects I see they have
like two-week iterations. Some one-week
works also well, but it depends also how
many teams are there on board and how
much coordination takes place. One to
two weeks is is a good number most of
the time. Okay, but what what goes on
there?
Let's take a typical
iteration ending starting day like I
will have tomorrow in the project I'm
working on right now.
And we start there by
um
presenting again what were the goals for
the iteration.
And then the teams report on what they
have achieved
during the iteration. So, first of all,
the commitment for the past iteration
and then what actually has been achieved
during that iteration. Then the teams
make a presentation of what they have
achieved. So, of the deliveries. That's
most of the time it's working software,
but sometimes the delivery could also be
something else. For example, if it's
like
um acquiring new skills and some people
have that task, then it's more report if
the workshop really did take place where
they spread the knowledge all over the
team. So, things like that could also be
a delivery.
Then the next thing we are doing is to
have a
retrospective and this depends on how
how long the iteration lasts and how
often we do this. So, at the beginning
of a project, normally a retrospective
takes about 1 hour. If the project is on
its way for a while, it's more like a 10
minutes, 15 minutes things because
things have been clarified. A
retrospective is a reflection on what
worked well and on things that need to
be improved. So, it's kind of a process
shaping
thing where everyone is is influencing
the the process. So, it could be like um
testing doesn't work the way we wanted
or the build breaks all the time, so we
have to do something about that. So,
it's sometimes very technical, sometimes
it's also like
um
our cast it's we have difficulties
accessing our customer if we need
clarification for something, so maybe
this needs to be escalated through
management to build up a better
communication channel to the customer.
So, it could be all kinds of thing.
Okay, after the retrospective um
we present so the customer
representative, this could be somebody
from inside the company just kind of
like a domain expert, business analyst,
but it could also be the the real
customer, depends on the project. Will
then uh present the goals for the next
iteration. So, asking things he wants to
to do and then the teams start planning
those things. So, plan the features and
split them into task, estimate them, and
then uh we come again together for the
final commitment. So, then the teams
say, "Okay,
this and that is what we are able to
do."
So, it could be that not all the goals
will be fulfilled or that there will be
a change in the goal, so like reducing
it or so that if they have figured out
that that it's too much they they should
plan for.
You are obviously in favor of Agile
development.
But, during the recent years, Agile
development has sort of
acquired a bad name in
in mainstream media coverage.
What would What would you suppose why
that is?
Maybe it's probably some sort of
misunderstanding. Maybe you'd like to
say some clarifying things about that.
I think I'm the wrong person because I
haven't realized that.
I can just tell you that at the moment a
lot of people, companies are asking me
to help them in many different ways. So,
one for example that I'm working on
projects as a coach or that they want to
jump start with a workshop or training
class or that they call me in for having
kind of a strange in that sense, but
like an assessment or
that that I could find out things they
could improve in their process. So, it's
the
Well, in the way I'm I'm busy. I
couldn't support the statement and I
don't know and what I also realize is
that a lot of the the big companies are
switching to agility and more like a
strategic thing even. So, it's not like
a single pilot project, but that they
say this is
the only chance we have at the moment.
So, I'm the wrong person.
So, um something that might support your
statement about the bad name of agility
is that I've heard about a conference
called Waterfall 2006. Are you involved
there? Have you been there or when is it
going to happen?
Well, it has happened and I was one of
the famous speakers there. It has
happened on April 1st
in Niagara.
Okay, and I think I'm not sure if I
remember my title correctly of my talk,
but it was something like
how to make teams so big that they are
not able to produce anything anymore.
Something like that.
So, you might have found out that this
was obviously an April's joke, but the
funny thing is that there was really a
call for papers. There was There was a
con- There's a conference website. I
think it's called waterfall2006.org
or something. So, it's really
professionally organized. So, you should
go to the website and and take a look.
And furthermore, there there really were
some serious
registration emails coming in and people
asking about the conference and really
wanted to go there. And well, I even
heard that
I think it was a professor who said,
"Well, I always thought that those
people like Kent Beck finally will
understand WHAT'S REALLY IMPORTANT."
YEAH, RIGHT. SO, because all the Agile
folks were involved in the planning,
according to the website.
Um do you want to elaborate a little bit
more on retrospectives?
Um I mean, probably that's something for
a separate podcast and we might want to
try to get Norm Kerth for this thing.
Um but um
the the the retrospectives that I have
been through as a participant have
lasted one or two days. Now, you talked
about a 10- or 15-minute retrospective.
Can you elaborate a little bit on what a
retrospective or what what what kinds of
different purposes a retrospective can
serve and and how to facilitate that
without going into too much detail,
probably?
So, um retrospectives they go back to
Norm Kerth in the software world. So,
that's So, it would be great if you
could interview Norm about that.
So, you could ask him.
Yeah, I can ask him.
Um
and
he when he wrote his book, he was mainly
focusing on end-of-project
retrospectives. And so, his book is also
called project retrospectives. And
now that you have talked about the the
length about the duration, the duration
of the retrospective
depends very much on the time frame
you're looking back at. So it's always a
looking back at what happened and then
learn from that and then plan for the
future. So the end is an action plan. So
it's kind of
yeah, a learning thing. And um
end of project of course it's at the end
of the project and very often a project
is kind of long so you might look at 2
years, 3 years or even a longer time
period and therefore you need more time
to learn from what happened there. Um
there are other retrospectives like
heartbeat retrospectives. That's what
I'm using a lot and this is kind like
like really the heartbeat the rhythm of
a project. So like after every iteration
do a quick reflection on what happened
in the past 2 weeks and then plan for
the changes for the next 2 weeks. And
you just look at 2 weeks and so not that
much has happened although at the
beginning you will figure that people
find a lot of things to improve. That's
very typical that at the beginning of
the project everyone says well this
doesn't work and we have to do that
better and so on. So you have a lot of
things to improve.
Um and after a while that's not true
anymore. Things have settled and
therefore not that much time is needed
then anymore. And at the beginning as I
said I often have like an hour or maybe
1 and 1/2 hours and after a while it
just there's not so much to look at
again and things are in in a good shape
and therefore the time goes also down to
what what's required for for
retrospective.
Okay, um there are
two more kinds of retrospectives. So the
other one is
work chunk retrospective. We call that.
This is when you have
accomplished a specific kind of work
chunk. For example, you have finished
release, a milestone, something like
that. And then you look back and how how
did that work? What can we do better?
And then the last kind of retrospective
is what we call a
customized um
retrospective. This is kind of after a
surprise. So, something has happened in
the project and you know want to know
why this happened, what you can do to
make it Yeah, I don't know. Whatever.
So, these are the different kinds. And
mainly in natural development we we said
like end of the project retrospective,
that's very important. But wouldn't it
be better to learn while we are on the
project and not only learn at the end
when it's all gone?
Especially because maybe the end of
project retrospective, they are
typically done after a failure. And so,
it's too late already. You cannot repair
the project anymore. And so, the idea is
to do this reflection more often and
learn from it. But it's not only finding
failures, but it's more also like
finding best practices and things like
that.
And the idea is probably that if you
have a team that does several projects
in a row, then according to I think it
was Alistair Cockburn, like you have to
finish or win the first game and then
prepare for the other one for the next
one. Then it probably makes sense to
have this postmortem retrospective to
prepare for the next project. But if you
have a 3-year project running, then it's
probably too late at the end.
One thing that that was that came to my
mind when we talked about improving the
process um couple of minutes ago, I
thought like CMM and CMMI is also about
uh those capability maturity levels are
also about improving the process
and steadily improving the process. So,
my question is, is there a tendency in
the community that some of the CMMI
folks recognize that Agile development
can help or is a way to become CMM
certified? Or the question is probably,
is there still this kind of opposition
between the CMM formality folks and on
the other side the Agile folks or is
there
recognition that this can go together
quite well?
Well, the major answer to that is that
it's
orthogonal to each other, so it's not
the same thing or you do either or
something like that. Um
the the CMMI folks, they are very often
at Agile conferences and there is an
exchange. There are also several papers
out there meanwhile um
saying how you can
combine that. Well, CMMI and and all
those certification certified processes,
they're mainly are you describe your
process and then you prove that you
follow your process. And
well, it's kind of joking, but there is
some truth in it. If you look at CMMI
CMMI level five,
this is more or less having
retrospectives all the time and learn
from it. However, you cannot jump from
zero to CMMI level five. So, that's kind
of why I say it's it's a bit like
joking, but that's always my major
answer. So, we are all doing CMMI level
five.
But, isn't CMM about having a
well-defined process that you follow all
the time, whereas Agile development is
like having a process for each project,
customized for each project?
Okay, but this depends on how you
document that process. So, if you have
in your process description that this is
part of it, adjusting it,
then it's it's because you follow
exactly that. Yeah. That Yeah, right.
It's It's more that you're just
documenting it then more on a meta
level. And this is fine. Although I
heard I don't know if it was what
Humphreys
I don't know. But I believe one one of
the CMI guys they said it often depends
on the auditor.
So, whoever will assess you
he could be fine with it or not. So, you
don't know really.
You know, lately you have worked a lot
in offshoring projects
and defining Agile or helping with
introducing Agile development into
offshoring projects.
From from my experience and what I
heard, this sounds very strange and I
find it very fascinating. Please tell us
more about it.
So, first of all in the setting I'm
typically in, this is more what what
people call nearshoring.
So, lucky lucky us in Europe, we have
the
the cheaper people in Eastern Europe.
So, this is most of the time the same
time zone. It's not so far away and
sometimes it's even uh um
as the same cultural history.
Especially so I'm I'm a lot in Austria
at the moment and Vienna is kind of the
portal to Eastern Europe. So, there's
Hungary is right in front of the door
and the Czech Republic and Poland is
close and and all those countries. And
um
for example
uh going from Brno to Vienna takes
I think less than an hour by car. So,
it's it's you have the
uh from the business point of view the
possibility to to
acquire cheaper resources, but you still
are able to meet face-to-face and I
think this is really one of the very
important things and that's what I also
know from other people which is more
typical in the States that they offshore
then to India. But what
well, speaking for the successful
projects, not for the other ones, for
the successful projects that always
meant that some people from India were
coming to the US and working on the
project for several months and then
going back. So it's again knowing the
people face-to-face, knowing who it is
and and know what's going on.
Um
most of the time also somebody from the
States then goes to India for knowing
what's going on there or to Russia. A
friend of mine say well
once he worked for a while in Russia, he
he finally realized with what kind of
things they are struggling with. For
example, that the power is down for
several hours a day and you are sitting
in the States and wondering why they're
not able to get that job done, but it's
if they are running out of power then
it's
well, they have to live with things like
that. Yeah.
And um
so really the most important thing is to
to get the people together so they know
each other. And then uh another thing is
to
to make sure that they are able to meet
from time to time. There's a time frame,
I'm not sure, it seems to be like around
10 weeks. That's at least what I
exchanged with with other colleagues.
That the trust goes down if you don't
meet each other face-to-face for for a
long period of time, then you are losing
trust. Except for you know each other
already very very well, then it's
different. So probably you all have
friends you don't meet for 2 years and
if you see each other then you are still
happy friends.
Um
it's different in a work life.
then for example, what what we also do
is we when we make the
stand-up meeting or daily scrum or or
this s-
I often call it just like regular
synchronization point. So, like
daily meeting.
Uh so, the whole team meets and
exchanges what's going on in the
project. Like, what every team member
has worked on since the last time we met
and what the person will work on till
the next time we will meet.
So,
um and we do this, for example, for the
for the teams who are not there, we
combine them with the conference call.
So, really an easy thing. We don't use
video conferencing because we we just
figured it's it's better to have simple
equipment, simple tools, and and make
that a quick thing. And this works well.
I would expect that when you work with
people in a different country, even if
you do meet face-to-face,
there are some cultural differences,
there's a different language. So, I
would expect that
a lot more documentation is needed.
Probably written documentation. Is that
true or
Okay. First of all, different languages.
I have a
I think a a good example from one of the
project I was on last year.
So, it was Hungary and Austria mainly.
And um
I think everybody understood German. So,
the Hungarians understood German. Uh
some of them were not able to speak it
that well. And then, if we had like the
synchronization thing, the stand-up
meeting, daily scrum I just mentioned,
um
via the phone, they all had really
difficulties in understanding. So, we
had this um practice where we said,
"Everyone has to speak in a foreign
language."
And this made it then that the Austrian
spoke a bit slower, used easier
vocabulary, so they spoke in English.
And most of the Hungarians they spoke in
German so whatever was better for them
and this was a really a good thing
because everyone used a simplified
vocabulary. Well, this is specific now
in our environment this probably you
will hardly find that if you are working
in the States for example because
English is just the only way you can go.
Maybe maybe if you work with South
America you can do the same with Spanish
and English could imagine. I don't know.
Okay now all right. I got regarding
cultural things.
Another thing I realized very often that
it's
a really different if you work with
people like from Eastern Europe that
they typically over commit. So it's very
difficult to
to make them aware of what they are
really able to accomplish during an
iteration and it always takes me long
discussions and arguments and and yeah
for trying to convince them that it's
more important to know what they are
really able to to achieve
and that it's not important that they
kind of overload themselves.
So I I really saw that the deadline was
far away far away but people
started already working overtime in
those iteration because they over
committed so much and our goal was
mainly to figure out what the real
velocity is and it was almost not
possible to figure that out because
really of the cultural thing and they
also told me that they have the
impression
that they are the
like the the honeybees though the
workers worker bees
who have to who just do a lot of stuff
and it's expected of them and it really
just like I
kind of with heart means had to convince
them that this is not the way we want to
do it like that and and that's a a
really typical cultural thing. Okay, and
you were asking about documentation.
That was the third question in in your
question.
So we use Wiki a lot which is super
because it's all over the place and you
don't have to send the documents back
and forth.
But of course we have more
documentation. For example, I like to
have uh the task planning normally on on
flip charts or with cards and things
like that, but we cannot
carry the cardboard with us or the flip
chart. It it doesn't make any
sense and so we use at the moment
for example Trek in the project I'm
working on right now. Trek is a kind of
a
a Wiki
and Trek comes from tracking. So it has
a ticketing system and we changed that a
little bit and it works pretty pretty
well for us for doing the iteration
planning. And so you can easily change
things like you can always do with a
Wiki, but you can also track things how
it's going on on in iteration. So we
have more things written down or more on
a I don't know more electronically
written down than we would normally
have. That's true.
Speaking of Wiki, the key idea of a Wiki
is that everybody can see and change
everything.
I sometimes heard that management was
skeptical about introducing a Wiki
because then there would was no quality
assurance and some employee who wanted
to harm the project could really really
harm the project. Has that ever happened
or how do you address this or is it not
an issue at all?
I hear that also. So there's the same
argument from management and well, the
only thing is that I always say from my
experience I've never seen that happen
and this is still true.
And
another thing is what what's most of the
time the more convincing than saying
that never has happened because of
course this company is different than
any other company and so on.
Uh is that most of the wikis meanwhile
have versioning.
And therefore you can always go back and
this is fine. And regarding quality
assurance, of course the things
documented on the wiki, they are not
meant to be quality assured. It's a
collaborative thing. However, what we do
very often is like developing
for example architectural concepts on
the wiki, but when there is a time where
we say, "Okay, this is now the status we
want to have." Then we produce a PDF for
example from it and this is then the
document we go with.
Regarding retrospectives, um
how many people
take place in there because you
mentioned you're working in teams with
200 and 300 people and you can't do
retrospectives with all of them, I
think.
Actually, this is similar to the
stand-up meeting, the daily scrum and so
on. For example, for a stand-up meeting
there are also limits how many people
can you bring together. It doesn't
matter if it's via phone or or
something. So, it's just it takes too
long. So,
there are two things with
retrospectives. So, one is to have a
staged retrospective meaning
retrospective in each team.
And most of the things that need to be
improved are actually things inside a
specific team. So, it's not so much
across teams. And then what we also have
like
across teams
a retrospective where we have like two
representatives or so from each team
coming together and then doing the
retrospective there together for
figuring out what's necessary across
teams. Or also they bring in some input
from the team retrospectives if there
are things everyone should be aware of
or just that the whole team can change
that.
Yeah, Yutta, thank you very much for the
interview. Great that you took the time.
You don't want to plug your book?
Okay, so this is the final
advertisement. Is that okay? Of course,
most of the things we have talked about
here I have written written them all
down in my book called Agile Software
Development in the Large, so you can
find answers to many of those questions
and of course of many questions we
haven't talked about now.
Thanks for giving me the chance to make
some advertisement.
No problem. Thanks.
This was another episode of Software
Engineering Radio.
The Software Engineering Radio team
wants to thank Henning Pauly for
providing the music as well as
lipsin.com for hosting and bandwidth.
For more information on the podcast,
past episodes, and feedback, go to
se-radio.net.